International politics and international relations
国际政治与国际关系的事情啊
Although international relations was one of my postgraduate majors
虽然来讲国关是我当初的进修的一个专业之一
However, many international issues are complex and intricate
但是呢很多的国际上的问题纷繁复杂
Today, we really need to talk about him.
到了今天咱们必须得讲一下他了
He's imposing these tariffs.
他这个加这关税
It's truly ridiculous, to be honest.
这事实在是让我感觉到非常的可笑啊
You see, no industry likes being guided by amateurs.
就是任何行业都怕这个外行指导内行啊
Amateurs guiding professionals is a really scary thing.
外行指导内行是一件非常可怕的事情啊
If you keep messing around like this,
你这么瞎搞的话
it can actually be quite dangerous at times.
其实有时候真的会很危险啊
And a lot of people are saying,
然后其实很多人就说
who exactly should be the right person for this?
这个到底应该什么样的人啊
To become a statesman
成为政治家啊
When talking about a statesman, the first thing to note is the need for a strong foundation in the humanities and social sciences.
我说政治家呢首先呢是需要有人文科学素养
And also, they need to have administrative experience at the grassroots level
又需要有基层的这种行政的经验
This is what it takes to be a qualified statesman.
这个东西来讲才能成为一个合格的政治家啊
In this regard
在这一点上来讲
The candidates we cultivate are thoroughly vetted by the UK The organization conducts very detailed reviews of all kinds And then their actual performance is evaluated Only then is there a possibility of promotion
我国培养的人来讲都是英国非常详细的啊 组织上啊非常详细的这种各种各样的审核呀 然后要看他的实际成绩 才有可能把他往上升啊
That's how it is.
是这样的
So the officials we select here,
所以我们这边来选出来的干部啊
many of them are extremely professional.
很多东西都是非常非常的专业的啊
But in the Western system,
但是西方这套体制来讲
someone might have been an actor yesterday,
他可能昨天是演员啊
or a drama teacher yesterday,
昨天是表演教师啊
like Zelensky,
比如说泽兰斯基
or the Little Potato,
比如说小土豆呃
It was the guest from yesterday's talk show, right?
昨天还是脱口秀的这个这个嘉宾对吧
For example, Trump
比如说特朗普啊
could become a political rising star tomorrow
明天就可以成为这个政治新星啊
I mentioned before that Musk is doing this funding
之前我说过马斯克做这个资
working on this Dogecoin
做这个这个dog
operating with this efficiency
做这个这个效率
the head of the resource department will have significant issues
这个资源部的这个主管会有很大的问题啊
and then, his stock prices have been plummeting lately
然后紧接着你像他的股票现在跌的声特别厉害
it’s not that there’s a rumor going around
不是说有一个传言说嘛
Rubio said he saw it
卢比奥说看见了
He was in the Oval Office, hugging a large picture of Trump.
说他在椭圆形办公室抱着那特朗普的大
Trump was crying on his thigh.
特朗普在大腿哭呢啊
When it comes to politics,
就说政治这个东西来讲
it's best not to let amateurs guide professionals.
最好是不要让这个外行指导内行
Let's talk about it.
咱们说啊
I often discuss the issue of Machiavellianism with everyone. Speaking of Machiavelli, if you don't read Machiavelli, it's actually about the traditional Western politics. You wouldn't understand. Especially in the Western world during the Renaissance era of the Middle Ages,
我经常跟大家说马加维利主义的问题 马加为利来讲 其实如果你不读马加维利的话 其实对于西方的这种传统政治 你是看不明白的 特别是在中世纪的哈文艺复兴时代的西方啊
For instance, let's say,
比如咱们说啊
if you see a rabbit,
如果有一只兔子
when you spot a rabbit,
你看见有一只兔子的时候啊
you should decisively get rid of it.
这时候应该就果断的把这只兔子杀掉啊
Why is that?
为什么呢
Because rabbits have a very strong reproductive rate.
因为兔子的繁殖力是非常强的
If you don't kill the first rabbit today,
你今天不杀第一只兔子
Tomorrow, it could be hundreds or even thousands.
明天就可能杀几百上千只啊
That’s why
所以这是为什么
In the Western era,
在西方时代的话
regarding religious heresy,
对于宗教异端啊
the eradication of cults
作为邪教的铲除
had to be particularly swift and decisive.
必须要特别的果断迅速啊
Because if you let it grow,
因为如果你一旦让它发展起来
many things are like this,
很多东西都是这样
you need to nip them in the bud.
你不在苗头啊去灭掉它
You need to eliminate it after it has developed.
你就要在它发展以后去灭掉它啊
That's truly terrifying.
这就非常的可怕了
However, Western countries often lack such governance experience.
但是西方国家往往没有这样的治理经验啊
And the tradition of such governance.
和这种治理的传统在里边
So, this is sometimes reflected in their administrative shortcomings.
所以呢呃这也是他们有时候行政上
Some things just don't work out.
有些东西会啊
They think for a long time.
想了半天
Now why many statesmen in Europe
现在为什么欧洲的很多政治家
Frankly, they are all second or third-rate statesmen.
说白了都是二三流的政治家
They're all a bunch of bleeding hearts.
都是一帮白左啊
Actually, a lot of the time, his skills are really far inferior to those of the past. Why can't we be saints at the second point? Especially medieval Europe you can't just be a like, for instance, the kingdom,
其实很多的时候 他的水平真的是比过去的人要差得远得多啊 第二点的时候为什么不能做圣母啊 特别是中世纪的欧洲 你不能去做一个 比如说咱们说王国啊
the Poland of the Age of Salvation,
拯救二时代的那个波兰的啊
or the Czech era in Europe.
捷克的那个时代的欧洲
So, you can't start by aiding refugees
那你首先不能去救济难民啊
Aiding refugees
救济难民
Assisting disaster victims
救济灾民
Including during epidemics and such
包括瘟疫之类的
If you're particularly kind-hearted
如果你一旦心眼儿特别好
You might start distributing supplies to the people
你开始开仓济民啊
But that's different from how our country operates
他跟咱们这样的国家是不一样
Our country is, well, unified in a grand way
咱们这样的国家是呃怎么说大一统的啊
We are an empire, after all
咱们这是一个帝国是吧
Whether it's the Qing Empire
无论是清帝国
or the Ming Empire
明帝国
it was an empire
这是一个帝国啊
in ancient times, during our feudal era
古代的时候咱们封建时代来讲哈
we actually weren't feudal
咱们其实不是封建啊
they established feudal states
他们是封建封邦建国
if you provided relief to disaster victims back then
如果你在那时候救济灾民啊
it wasn't a unified action
不是一种统一的行为的话
once you started providing relief to disaster victims
一旦你这边开始救济灾民
Refugees
难民啊
These refugees
你这些难民啊
Disaster victims will flock to your city-state
灾民啊都会往你这个城邦涌入
This will cause your economy to collapse immediately
这样你的经济马上就崩溃啊
So in medieval Europe, quite often,
所以在中世纪的欧洲很多的时候来讲的话
It’s not a matter of one side being benevolent
不是你一方人用得了好心的
Sometimes, being a statesman requires having a heart of stone.
有的时候做政治家就必须要心非常的狠心
Being extremely ruthless is necessary The principles of Western politics differ from those of Eastern politics It's quite different, relatively speaking. But when we talk about the Legalist school of thought, including what Han Feizi discussed, there are many aspects to consider.
非常的黑才行啊 所以来讲说西方政治的理念跟东方政治的理念 相对来讲的话是非常的不一样的 但是我们说法家的东西 包括韩非子是讲了很多东西来讲的话
If you truly understand him,
如果你要是真是了解他的话
you'll realize that the Legalists talk about the dark rules of politics.
你会知道法家讲的是政治的一个黑暗的规律
As I mentioned earlier, the theory of killing the rabbit,
就像我刚才说的杀兔子这个理论
or we could say, this theory about not being able to aid refugees,
或者咱们说这个这个这个这个不能救济难民的
this theory,
这个理论啊
and there's also a third theory.
还有一个第三个理论
So, are you referring to primogeniture?
就是说如果你的因为是嫡长子继承制吗
If your wife's relatives are very powerful,
如果你的妻子的亲族非常厉害
you're likely to be poisoned in your old age.
那你大概率会在晚年中毒死掉
Because establishing a region,
因为确立一个地方的这个啊
as you get older,
一个这个因为你老了以后
you'll keep having children,
你会不停的生孩子呀
right?
对不对
After having children, you'll grow fond of them,
你生孩子以后你会喜欢孩子
and the young children's mothers.
年轻的孩子的妈妈
Is that right?
对不对
Then the relatives of those people might take advantage of it.
那那帮人的亲族可能就占便宜了
So, at that time,
所以到那个时候来讲
the more wives you have,
如果你娶的老婆越多的话
it actually turns into a power struggle over inheritance.
其实就一个继承权的权力斗争啊
Throughout history,
自古以来
the safest method has been to promote the heir to a higher position. promoting the heir early, What should we do then? Right? So, dying would be the best option for you. If his relatives aren’t powerful, he’s the one who will end up dead. Because there will be others who want to take his place. So why are you playing Crusader Kings
所以最安全的方法就是继承人提倡上位 那继承人提前上位 那是怎么办呢 对吧 那就是你死掉了就是最合适的 如果他的亲族不厉害 那死掉的一定是他 因为有别人想去取代他的位置啊 所以为什么你玩什么十字军之王
some wives whose family isn’t strong often
有些老婆他家族能力不强的时候
end up being poisoned to death.
经常会被中毒死亡的
This is actually a very realistic issue.
其实这是一个非常现实的问题啊
In reality, all countries have issues of inheritance.
现实当中所有的国家来讲都会有这个继承权的
This is also a matter of war.
这战争之问题啊
This isn't just about ancient times, though.
这也不光是古代对
Look at what the U.S. is doing now.
你看美国现在这么一弄啊
Actually, I generally avoid commenting on American affairs.
其实我一般不愿意去评价美国这些事
Because when it comes to these things,
因为他的这些东西来讲的话
once you start commenting,
一评价了以后呢
it's easy to open a can of worms,
就很容易就是说打开一个呃口子以后
and find it's full of maggots.
就发现里边全是蛆
This is exactly the kind of issue.
就是这种问题啊
So his problem is actually very serious.
所以他的问题其实非常的严重
You can't give this to someone who isn't a traditional statesman.
就是你不能给这种就是不是传统政治家的人
Excessive power.
过大的权利
Of course,
当然来讲的话
By doing this,
他这么一搞的话
It's very likely to exacerbate the problem.
就容易特别的容易的把他这个问题搞坏了
As I often say,
就因为啊我经常说啊
A competent statesman should have a very good command of the humanities and social sciences. But I've always advised everyone to do this When you're young and your brain is sharp Learn science and engineering when you have the physical strength When you're older, in your thirties or forties, around my age
一个合格的政治家应该是人文学科学的非常好 但是我一直建议大家是这样 年轻的时候脑子好的时候 体力好的时候学理科学工程啊 老了以后三四十岁到我这个岁数啊
Your energy isn't what it used to be
人也不行了
Your physical functions decline
机能也不行了
That's when you can turn to studying history, geography, and politics
这时候再去研究史地政啊
Study historiography
研究历史学
Study sociology
社会学
Political science
政治学
the study of international relations
研究国际关系学
psychology
心理学啊
and some philosophy and such
还有一些哲学这些东西来讲的话
we can say that these six subjects can be learned even when we're older
咱们说这六科其实可以老了以后再学习啊
especially
特别是来讲的话
not knowing history is quite dangerous
不读历史是很危险的
because
因为来讲的话
the last tariff increase
上次加关税
In the 1920s and 1930s in America, tariffs were haphazardly added.
在美国的二三十年代胡服那个时代乱加关税
This led to an economic crisis.
那就是说就引引发过一次经济危机
Prior to that, it was also between the UK and the US.
在之前还演也是英美之间的
Trade between European countries also triggered an economic crisis.
欧洲之间的贸易也引发过经济危机
World War I was, to some extent, sparked by such issues.
一战其实也是在一定程度上就是这么引起的
If you don't study history,
所以你不学历史的话
you'll fall into a global recession.
就会陷入一种全球的衰退
That's how it started.
就是这么开始的
So if you do this,
所以你这样搞的话
It would ruin the economies of all countries
就弄得各国的经济都完蛋
Now, talking about it
那么来讲的话
Our countermeasures were absolutely timely
咱们说咱们的反制措施是绝对来得及时的
Because if you don’t act in time It would be useless And the more we talk about it now You have to force the other side to back down So, there’s no other way That’s just how it is So, you're not a professional statesman.
因为如果你反制不及时 那就等于没有用 而且越到这个时候来讲的话 你就必须逼着对方下场啊 所以来讲的话这个东西是没有办法的啊 这个东西来讲 所以说你不是职业的政治家的事
There are certain things you just don't understand.
有些东西你就不懂
Often, it's not what you imagine.
很多的时候来讲
It's not how you picture it in your mind.
不是说你想象中怎么样
For instance, when he asked KUSHA to find an economist,
你像他当初委托KUSHA去找一个经济学家
I just found an author of a bestseller on Amazon
直接就在亚马逊上找了一个畅销书的作者
Turns out, the author mostly cited their own work.
结果那作者其实还是自己引用自己的那个
To create a piece of work.
做一个作品啊
You can find related information in English news reports.
这个相关的资料你可以看英文的报道
He has mentioned this issue before.
其中就讲过这个问题
Regarding the tariffs he imposed,
就是说他他对于加关税
the impact on the economy is a concept he's not well-versed in.
会对经济的影响的这个概念
Actually, he didn't study this field.
其实他并不是学这个的
As for the actual effects of tariffs,
至于关税到底有什么样的影响
he doesn't even know what the RAF is used for.
其实他也不知道这胎RAF到底干什么用的
So, he believes that
所以这个东西他就认为
this will lead to the return of manufacturing jobs.
这样就会造成制造业回流
But if he truly wants to bring manufacturing back,
可是如果他真想让制造业回流的话
It's what should be done
应该是应该干的
It's about invading Canada or Mexico
是入侵加拿大或者入侵墨西哥啊
And then invade Greenland
然后再入侵格陵兰
Once you successfully invade Mexico You'll gain a large manufacturing workforce Effectively bringing manufacturing back to the U.S. It's unlikely that these people will regain control of the manufacturing industry Because these American workers
一旦你把墨西哥给入侵成功了啊 你就会得到大量的制造业人口 实际上让制造业回归美国 让这帮人他们重新掌握制造业是不太可能的 因为这些美国的工人
To put it bluntly, they lack the modern skills
咱们说白了他没有具备现代啊
A kind of worker's quality
呃一种工人的一种啊素养啊
Whether it's in terms of physical fitness
不管是从他的体能上
Or for instance, when there's nothing to do
还是说比如说没事
Some people have a more laid-back lifestyle
有些人啊生活上比较放飞自我
So their physical fitness might not be as good
那体能上可能不太好
They wouldn't be as tough as Mexican workers
他不会有那些墨西哥工人更厉害
So if he has these Mexican workers under his control
所以如果他把这些墨西哥工人搁在手里了
And also has the resources from Canada and Greenan
再把加拿大资源跟格林安资源拿在手里了
Other countries would really have no way to deal with him
别的国家还真没有办法对付他啊
And his defense stocks will soar.
而且他这些军工股就会大涨
So these things of his,
所以他的这些东西
his MUA groups will become even more fanatical.
他这些MUA啊群体就会更狂热
But if you do this,
但如果你这么弄的话
the economy will keep deteriorating,
经济越来越不行啊
and the people's livelihood will suffer more,
然后民生凋敝的话
which will expedite the downfall of the Trump administration.
这个东西会加速他这个特朗普政权的完蛋
Especially with Musk getting involved,
特别是那马斯克也是上来
you just cut the staff.
你就裁员
You know this thing about layoffs
你知道这个东西裁员
This thing is like toilet paper
这东西呢就像这个擦屁股纸一样
This piece of toilet paper
你这一张擦屁股纸
It might only have 20% used 80% of it is unused But if you cut that 80% off It just leaves the part with... you know If that 20% is all there is You’ll end up with it all over your hands
他可能只有20%的地方 有史80%的地方没有屎 但是如果你把那80%都撤了的话 只是让擦到屎 那20%的存在的话 那你就满手都会是屎
There are so many things
很多的东西
Many positions are like this
很多的职位就是这样
When he's not contributing anymore
他再不发挥作用的时候
You think he's no longer useful
你觉得他没有作用啊
It's like a company thinking it's all about sales
就像一个公司说有销售就完了啊
Or it's all about R&D
有研发就完了
Then there's HR and administration, all over the place
那人事行政乱七八糟的
What about maintenance
什么维护
What's the point of all that mess
什么乱七八糟那些有什么用啊
What's the point of public relations?
什么公关有什么用啊
What's the use of marketing?
市场有什么用啊
Everything was given to him.
全给他开了
But when you really open everything up,
可是你真把它全开的时候
When only sales and R&D are left,
只剩销售跟研发的时候
You realize you can't do anything.
你发现你什么事都干不了
Many things are like this.
很多东西都是这样
Isn't the car just the wheels turning?
那车不就是轮子在转吗
It's the wheels that keep everyone moving.
是轮子在带动大家在转啊
So, wouldn't the car just need wheels and a body?
那车就有轮子跟壳不就完了吗
Hey, you realize you need wheels and a body.
嘿你发现你要有轮子跟壳
What about the drive shaft?
什么传动轴
What a mess.
什么乱七八糟的
What about the throttle and other components?
什么节流阀什么之类的都不用的话
That would be a disaster, right?
那就完蛋了对吧
So, that's how it often is.
所以很多的时候就是这样
So, when we talk about anything,
所以来讲我们说啊任何事情来讲
we shouldn't let amateurs guide experts.
都是不能让外行指导内行
If he continues on this path,
他这么着继续去搞的话
the global economy will fall into recession.
全球经济会陷入衰退
That's a given.
这个是啊毋庸置疑的啊
And I'm not even talking from an economic standpoint, because when it comes to economics, I'm a layman. But from the statesman's perspective, speaking philosophically, Machiavelli was quite clear, politics, after all, is about...
而且我也不从这个经济上来讲 因为经济上来讲 我是个外行 但是咱从这个政治家的角度来讲的话 马加亚维利说的其实很清楚啊 其实政治呢他到底是什么呢
It's a synthesis that balances the interests of all parties.
它是一个平衡各方关系利益的一个合成啊
For many people,
很多人来讲的话
they think all the tricks are in one hand.
认为啊我一招全在一手
Turning a single advantage into a hundred.
便把利来行变百令来行
Actually, being a good manager,
实际上啊当好一个管理者
a manager with political power,
当好一个就拥有政治权利的一个管理者啊
is not easy at all.
其实想治理好是非常不容易的
The so-called art of politics,
所谓的政治上的艺术
political science
政治political science
Science
科学
when it comes to many things
很多东西来讲的话
in terms of governance
治理来讲
it involves the hearts and minds of people
它涉及到人心向背
it involves economic principles
涉及到经济规律
it involves military conflict
涉及到军事斗争
and intelligence operations
情报上的斗争
in fact, much of the time it's a very complex matter
其实很多的时候它是一种非常复杂的事情
like when Netanyahu goes for an interview today
你就像今天内塔尼亚胡去采访啊
Not for an interview
不是去采访
To pay a visit to Trump, huh
去拜会特朗普哈
When is the best time to establish a friendship with someone
什么时候是跟一个人建立友谊的最佳时机
It's when they are deserted by everyone
就是他众叛亲离的时候啊
Trump is at the lowest point in his life right now So offering him a helping hand at this moment Would be very useful Jews are business people Jews are very smart Netanyahu is a figure that everyone wants to distance themselves from at this stage.
特朗普现在处于他人生中的最低点 所以这个时候向他伸出援手来讲的话 是非常有用的啊 犹太人是做生意的人 犹太人脑子很聪明 内塔尼亚胡是也是一个人人喊打的一个阶段
So, at this point,
所以这个阶段来讲的话
if any place,
其实如果任何地方啊
country or business group,
国家或者商业团体啊
or intelligence organization,
或者说情报组织
if you move closer to Israel now,
你这个时候如果跟以色列走近的话啊
it’s actually the best time to show goodwill towards Israel.
其实是现在向以色列卖好的一个最佳时机
That is to say, if you’re not overtly, for example, as a country,
也就是说如果你在明面上不比如国家来讲的话
you can’t have relations with Israel.
你不能跟以色列来往
But at this point, you are a business group
但是这个时候你是商业团体
or some other entities
你是一些其他的啊
such as law enforcement agencies
一些执法部门
if you engage in unofficial interactions with Israel
如果你这时候你跟这个以色列啊
at this time, they would feel quite
进行一些非官方的交往的话来讲的话
how to put it
这时候他会感觉到非常的呃
appreciated
怎么说呢
Getting attention
受到关注啊
making it more effective than usual
它会比平时更有效
It's not that what they do is just.
并不是说啊他们做的事情是正义的啊
It's precisely because what they do is unjust.
正是因为他们做的事情是不正义的
They are in a phase where they have lost support from all sides.
属于一种啊众叛亲离的阶段
This is the time when any political support for them,
这个时候来讲对他的进行任何的啊政治上的
or private relationship enhancement,
还有私下的关系上的这种增加呢
is actually the best opportunity. So, in this sense, it's like the most unpopular kid in your class, the ones who are least liked by everyone. If you suddenly start being particularly nice to him, he will rely on you, he will depend on you.
其实是一个最佳的时机 所以来讲的话 这就像你班里边最招人讨厌的孩子啊 最不招人待见的那些人 你如果对他突然特别好的话 他就会仰赖你 他就会依赖你啊
And when two people who were especially bad with each other suddenly,
而突然之间那两个关系都特别不好的人
they tend to team up.
他们容易结对子啊
That's how it goes.
就是这样
Then they become a menace that everyone wants to get rid of.
然后成为人人喊打的一个祸害
But speaking of it,
但是来讲的话
we're talking about some political matters today.
咱们说咱们今天讲的还是政治上的一些东西啊
There are things you should do and things you shouldn't.
一些什么东西该做什么东西不该做啊
In many cases,
很多的时候来讲
so you need to understand,
所以你要明白
if you don't know political science,
如果不懂政治学
or international relations,
不懂国际关系学
in many situations,
很多的时候来讲的话
you also don't know economics,
你又不懂经济学啊
you have no knowledge of the humanities,
人文的学科你一概都不懂啊
you can only improvise.
你只能乱弹
You can only use the art of people's hearts.
你只能用那些人心啊
The art of deals, you know.
那些交易的艺术啊
Why do I dare to criticize Trump?
我为什么敢批评他特朗普呢
Because I've read his books, like The Art of the Deal.
因为他的那些书我都看过交易的艺术啊
He's actually a very successful
他其实是一个非常成功的一个
narcissistic type of player.
自恋型的这么一种选手啊
Narcissistic Personality Disorder, or NPD.
自恋型的NPD
You could say he has NPD.
你可以说他是NPD
But you could also argue he doesn't quite reach the stage of NPD.
但其实也可以说他不到NPD的阶段
When it comes to manipulating people's emotions, he's quite skilled.
他玩弄人心这方面来讲哈
Especially in interpersonal matters, he does pretty well. But he has a keen understanding of social structure, and the international relations and geopolitical landscape, economic matters, diplomatic issues, and such, especially political matters,
特别是人之间的东西还是可以的啊 但是他对于社会结构啊 对于这个国际之间的这种啊关系局势 对于经济啊 对于外交之类的东西来讲啊 特别是政治上的一些东西
he might not be as knowledgeable.
他可能还是不是那么的清楚啊
Let's talk about the various eras in Chinese history.
咱们说中国的历史时期经过各种各样的啊时代
For example, there was the Eastern Jin Dynasty
比如说有东晋啊
with its aristocratic clans
有这个氏族啊
an era of political rise
政治崛起的时代
and during the Ming Dynasty, there was the Cabinet
有这个明朝有内阁
right?
对不对
and the Qing and Yuan Dynasties
有清朝跟元朝啊
had various noble and elite groups
有这种各种各样的啊贵族精英集团
so in many cases
所以很多的时候来讲
over the centuries
千百年来啊
We have always been in conflict with these clan groups
我们一直是在跟这些氏族集团啊
elite groups
精英集团啊
and noble factions
贵族集团啊在进行斗争啊
But in the era of the people, things are different
到了人民的时代又是不一样
So, when it comes to many aspects
所以很多东西来讲
We are unique throughout history
我们都是千古以来独一份
And we have a wealth of
而我们有丰富的这种啊
historical experience to draw upon
历史上的经验可以去参考啊
for any matter
任何事情
For instance, the Five Barbarians' Invasion
比如五胡乱华啊
or the Migration of the Gentry to the South
比如衣冠南渡
In many cases
很多的时候来讲
what's trivial and what's significant
什么轻什么重啊
how much effort should be applied to what
什么东西该用几分力
we are quite clear about that
咱们是非常清楚的啊
For example, when it comes to dealing with cults
比如说对待邪教的问题
we are absolutely clear
咱们是非常非常清楚
and very decisive Because historically, we've suffered from this issue far too many times. For example, the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom Of course, everyone has a different concept of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom. Some people say,
非常非常果断的 因为历史上吃这个亏吃的实在是次数太多了啊 比如说太平天国啊 当然来讲每个人说太平天国的概念是不一样啊 有人说啊
The Taiping Heavenly Kingdom was revolutionary.
太平天国那是革命的
That's different.
那不一样啊
Of course, the perspective varies.
当然来讲这个角度不一样
The angle makes a difference.
从角度来讲不一样
So, that should be to erase it.
那那这应该就是泯灭他
Right or wrong
对不对
But you have to look at it from the perspective of the people's revolutionary history
但是你要从人民革命的历史的
If we view it from this people's historical perspective
这个人民史观来看的话啊
The Taiping Heavenly Kingdom was also a proactive force in various ways.
太平天国又是一个积极的怎么样
However, speaking of which
但是来讲的话
If we carefully analyze it
咱们如果去详细的去分析
Regarding the entire process of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom
太平天国整个这个过程来讲的话
Of course, when we talk about it
当然来讲的话
This is a case of everyone having their own interpretation
这个就是公说公有理
Well, everyone has their own reasons.
婆说婆有理啊
It doesn't really matter.
没有什么关系
Let me tell you something.
咱们哎我跟你讲
Guys just love to argue about history and military stuff.
男生就是爱在历史上军事上的问题上吵啊
So, it includes both arts and sciences.
所以包括文理科
All these things in history.
包括历史上所有这些东西
As long as it's a guy,
只要是男生
Once you mention it, they're drawn in.
你一说他就给他吸引过来了
And if the concept is different from his,
然后只要概念跟他不一样
He just scolded
他就骂
And that's how it is
然后就是这样
Then the traffic picked up
然后流量就起来了
That's just how it works
这个东西就是这样
So today, we're still talking about any issue
那咱们今天还是说任何事情啊
There's always the problem of amateurs not guiding professionals So, it still comes down to the statesman Professional statesmen deal with political issues And professional diplomats handle diplomatic issues Professional economists deal with economic issues.
都有一个外行不要指导内行的一个问题啊 所以来讲还是让政治家 职业的政治家去处理政治上的问题 让职业的外交家去处理外交上的问题啊 职业的经济学家处理经济上的问题啊
Some people say,
有人说啊
I know more than they do.
我比他们都懂
It's precisely because you know nothing,
正是因为你什么都不懂
that you feel you understand more than others.
所以你会觉得你比别人更懂呃
Because of belief,
因为信仰啊
knowledge has its own gaps.
知识它是有一个一个沟壑的
When you first start out,
当你刚一开始的时候
you think you understand everything.
你是觉得你什么都懂的
After some time has passed
到了过一段时间
you'll find yourself in a profound and deep challenge
你会发现你进入一个非常强大的一个深渊
it's at this moment that you learn how to
就是这个时候你学习怎么着
feel like you can't climb out of this abyss
你觉得就从这深渊上爬不上来
but later, when you've learned a great deal
等到后来你学的特别丰富的时候
you'll realize
你会发现哦
that you've become more balanced
原来你就平和了
it's just like that
就是这样
when you first start to understand
在刚懂的时候
Just like when you start practicing martial arts
就像刚练武术一样
You really love challenging others to a match
特别爱跟人比武啊
But as you practice more and more
你真正武术练得多了
And see more masters
高手见得多了
You won't be so eager to engage in life-or-death duels
你就不太想跟别人进行生死决斗了啊
Because those things can't be resolved through life-or-death duels
那些东西来讲通生死决斗也看不出来
So a person with a lot of knowledge won't compete with others
所以来讲一个知识多的人是不会跟人争高下的
On the contrary, someone with less knowledge
放相反一个知识啊
Is often more eager to prove themselves
不满啊
A half-bottle of water
一瓶子半瓶子水
A half-bottle of vinegar is bustling about This person tends to easily get into verbal spats with others So I’ve been through my teens and twenties too Right? So I understand that tendency to argue To argue with people on Zhihu and Baidu Tieba
半瓶子醋使劲在那逛荡啊 这个人是容容易跟人家起口角的 所以我也是从十几岁20岁过来的 对不对 所以我也知道那个爱起口角 爱在知乎上跟百度的贴吧上跟人家吵架
What kind of state that is
是一种什么样的状态
How about I post it on my Tieba?
要不我的贴贴吧
How did this episode of Tu Latin 83 come about?
这图拉丁83集是怎么过来的
Right?
对不对
You must have had an argument with someone.
肯定跟人吵过架
So, in the grand scheme of things, it doesn’t really matter.
所以这一切的事情来讲都无所谓
But you, Trump,
但是你特朗普
as the leader of a country,
你作为一国的一个首脑
you also do this?
你也这么搞
Musk is with his two NPDs
马斯克跟他两个NPD在一起
That would be absolutely terrifying
那就这就太可怕了
You know
你知道吗
Two NPDs
两个NPD啊
It's like a pair of twins
这简直就是双子星
Complementing each other
互相成就
Validating each other
互相认证
Constantly flattering each other
互相又拍对方的马屁
And emotionally relying on each other
互相又在精神上依赖对方
That's a truly frightening situation
这就是一个非常可怕的事情
The scariest thing is that humans lack a frame of reference.
最可怕的就是这个人类没有一个参照系
You know that, right?
知道吧
Tang Taizong had Wei Zheng, after all.
你说唐太宗有魏征啊
So, a lot of the time,
所以很多的时候来讲
no one tells you
没有人告诉你
that what you're doing is wrong.
你做的事情是错的
He would tell you
他所有的事情告诉你
that everything you do is right. In other words, it's like an emperor and a eunuch. When two people are together, they say to each other Oh, Your Majesty, you are truly wise And the eunuch says to the Emperor, and the eunuch says Oh, that Zhao Gao You really understand my thoughts and all
你做的事情都是对的啊 也就是说白了就是一个皇帝跟一个太监 两个人在一起互相说 哎呀皇上你太英明了 还太监说跟皇上跟太监说 哎呀那个那个赵高 你实在是那个深知我心想之类
This is a disaster
这就完蛋
This can easily lead to the decline of a dynasty
这就容易引起王朝末期
So I think in many cases
所以我现在觉得很多的时候来讲的话
We must not, well, how to put it
咱们一定不要把呃怎么说呢
Wear a frown
悲观挂在脸上
But in reality, you need to be prepared for the worst-case scenario
但是在现实当中要准备好这个最坏的结局啊
Because a cornered dog will jump over the wall
因为这个狗急了跳墙
There are many things that can go wrong
这是一定的好多事情来讲说不好啊
Considering everything
因为所有的事情
If there’s a process of things turning for the worse
只要他有像坏的方向转变的过程的话
It will definitely turn that way
就一定会这么转变啊
This is like Moore's Law
这就是摩尔定律啊
So many things aren’t actually governed by Moore's Law
所以很多啊不是不是摩尔定律
It's Murphy's Law.
是摩菲定律啊
So, a lot of the time,
所以很多的时候来讲
the more you know,
你知道的东西越多啊
the less happy you might be,
反而你高兴不起来
the less likely you are to argue with others.
你反而不会想跟人吵架
That's how it is.
就是这样
But when it comes to politics,
但是政治上来讲的话
it's best to leave it to the professionals.
还是要交给专业的人来做啊
Still, I'll say it again
还是我那句话啊
The country is making adjustments to the humanities
呃国家进行这个文科的
Many universities are adjusting their humanities and science departments
很多的大学进行这个文科理科的院系的调整
I think that's right
我觉得这是对的啊
Because when it comes to the humanities It doesn't really help you find a job It's about cultivating humanistic literacy It shouldn't be used as a major in college We're not like in the West where people study humanities and then go to law school
因为我觉得文科这个东西来讲呢 对你求职没有帮助啊 它是一种人文素养的培养啊 不应该作为一种大学的一个专业来使用啊 咱们跟那个西方的这种学了文科进法学院
And then enter politics
然后再进入政界
That's not the same thing
那不是一个关系啊
So to say
所以来接
If you want to contribute to the country
我觉得如果你要想建设好国家来讲的话
In your twenties and thirties
在二三十岁的时候
You should learn things that are easier to find jobs with
还是要学习一些比较容易找到工作
Easier to
比较容易啊
Engage in social and practical production
进行这个怎么社会生产方面实践方面的东西啊
More practical things
更学更实用的东西啊
The humanities, especially history books
人文这些特别是历史书啊
You can read them when you're in your thirties and forties
你完全可以在你三四十岁的时候再读啊
By then, you'll be like me, older
这个时候你也像我一样老了
Wiser and more experienced
老谋深算
You'll have seen more
看的也多了
And truly understand why politics works the way it does
你也真正能明白了政治为什么是这么回事
Because when you're young, you don't understand
因为你年轻的时候你不懂
When you're young, you're full of passion
年轻的时候你一定是啊一腔热血啊
Young
年轻啊
How can this passion ever cool down
怎么这个这个我这热血怎么能让我冷了呢
Right
对不对
How can I be put in the fridge
怎么能把我放进冰箱了
But after a while
但是时间长了以后
You'll realize
你就会发现啊
There are certain rules in politics that are correct
政治上有些规律是对的
Sometimes you can't be merciful
有时候就是不能心慈手软
Sometimes you can't talk about morals and righteousness
有的时候就是不能讲仁义道德
Sometimes in international relations Military conflicts Intelligence battles All kinds of economic struggles You have to fight back Fighting back is sometimes unavoidable Because once you show mercy You suffer
有的时候在国与国啊 军事斗争 情报斗争啊 各种各样经济斗争的时候 就是要以牙还牙 以牙还牙这东西是没有办法的 因为你一旦仁慈啊 你倒霉
Your side will suffer
你的这一方的人就会倒霉
So in this regard
所以这个东西来讲的话
It's like team battles
就是打团战啊
Playing competitive games
打这种竞技服
In ranked matches
打这种排位服的时候
You need to have a ruthless heart
就要有一个非常狠的一个心才行
So in these matters
所以这些东西来讲的话
It's always the same
永远都是那样啊
An outsider shouldn't guide an expert
一个外行不要去指导内行
Don't be like Trump
既不要去当特朗普
We shouldn't be like Trump
咱们自己也不要当特朗普
Going around pointing out flaws
然后闲着没事去指点江山之类的
Rest assured
你要放心啊
A country has its most elite people
一个国家里有一个国家的最精英的人
All working on it
都是在那啊
No need to worry about these issues
不用去担心这些问题啊
So in the end
所以来讲更多的来讲的话
We should focus on ourselves
咱们关心好自己就好了